Guide to Central Washington University Bowers Field Collection 2020
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections
Bowers Field Collection
1958-2006
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections 400 E University Way Ellensburg, WA 98926 (509) 963-1717 http://www.lib.cwu.edu/Archives-Special-Collections archives@cwu.edu
MS020
5 cubic feet Seven (7) boxes total ( six letter sized and one oversized flat box.)
Historical Note
Bowers Field Airport was named after Ensign Robert Keith Bowers, Ellensburg’s first native son killed at the attack on Pearl Harbor during World War II.
Beginning in 1926, civilian aviation developed at Ellensburg, with aircraft initially operating from a privately-owned golf course which served as a landing strip. In 1930, a graded runway was constructed by the County and aviation enthusiasts, with a crosswind (7-25) built in 1936 with Civil Aeronautics Administration (CAA) funds and work program labor. The airport was sold to the City of Ellensburg in 1938, as airfield improvements were further implemented under governmental jurisdiction and as flight training programs and other airport activity increased to respond to wartime aviation needs.
In the early 1940’s Bowers Field was expanded through the CAA’s DLAND program (Development of Landing Areas for National Defense) as a leased military airfield for the 4th Air Force Bomber Base and then a Bowers Field Airport, Kittitas County, Washington tactical fighter sub-base serving the west coast command.
An auxiliary airport was built by the Army Air Corps in 1943 for cadet training north of Smithson Road. During this period, the airfield received extensive infrastructure improvements though government and military funding programs, including the paving and expansion of the runways (4,500’), a control tower, and support buildings, housing and hangars.
In 1947, Bowers Field was declared military surplus and deeded to Kittitas County, resulting in the deactivation, closure and further abandonment of military airfield and landside infrastructure (primarily west and east of the airfield). In the late 1940’s, airline service was initiated by Empire Airlines at Bowers Field as a locally owned regional carrier. Later, another regional carrier service was attempted for Ellensburg.
From 1957 to 1961 the City of Ellensburg assumed ownership of Bowers Field. In 1961 it reverted to County control. During this period, Midstate Aviation emerges from the purchase of Ellensburg Flying Service, as general aviation responds to military flight training needs. In 1965, the newly formed Port District assumes operation of Bowers Field, but is dissolved in 1973, after which Kittitas County again reassumes airport control.
During the 1990’s airport facilities were upgraded, including the extension of utilities to the south side industrial area to support further business development and airport facility expansion. Central Washington University, during 1990, began a Flight Technology program under contract with Midstate Aviation, offering a four-year degree program that resulted in the construction of new terminal building facilities and a dedicated college classroom building. In 2001, an Airport Master Plan Update was initiated and a comprehensive Zoning Ordinance passed which protects Bowers Field from non-compatible land use development.
The records of the Bowers field collection include correspondence, a scrapbook, maps, and official documents.
Original Order
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bowers Field Archives
Aviation; Airports; Flight training
Scrapbooks; Washington (State); Transportation
- MEIGS, 2003-2003 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Land Use Regulation Civil Airports, Glover, 1994-1994 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Caltrans Airpot Land Use Brochure (Box-folder 1-3)
- Land Lease-Airport, 2002-2006 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Airport Insurance/EAA, 1986-2002 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Idaho Pilot Assoc. Newsletter-"The Fliyline" Part 1, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Idaho Pilot Assoc. Newsletter-"The Fliyline" Part 2, 2000-2005 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Gate Key Policy, 1999-2007 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Fuel Tax-State (Box-folder 1-9)
- Flight Systems, 2000-2000 (Box-folder 1-10)
- FAROS (Final Approach Runway Occupancy Signal), 2006-2006 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Federal Aviation Regulations (FAR) Part 77 (Box-folder 1-12)
- EAA Publicity, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 1-13)
- California Pilots Assoc.-Newsletter, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Bowers Report/Appointments to Advisory Board, 2002-2002 (Box-folder 1-15)
- AOPA Airport Support Network, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Airport-Public Relations/AOPA Brochure, 2003-2003 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Airport Closure-Website, 2007-2007 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Airport Appreciation, 1998-1998 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Regulation Standards-AOPA/Airport Support, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Regulations-Working Doc., 1992-2002 (Box-folder 1-21)
- Regulations-FAA Adisory, 1958-2000 (Box-folder 1-22)
- Wind Farms, 2004-2004 (Box-folder 1-23)
- General Aviation News/Airport Adisory Committee/Mission Statement, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 1-24)
- Airport Development Costs/Airport Security, 2003-2003 (Box-folder 1-25)
- - (Box-folder -)
- FLABOB/AOPA's Guide/Airport Authorities (Box-folder 2-1)
- Hangar Ground Leases (Box-folder 2-2)
- Residential Airpark-Bowers (Box-folder 2-3)
- Airport Park (Box-folder 2-4)
- Bowers Arguments/Young Eagles Letters (Box-folder 2-5)
- UGA-Bowers (Box-folder 2-6)
- Central Washington Soaring (Box-folder 2-7)
- U.S. Department of Labor/Recommendations Land Lease/Airport Open House, 2006-2006 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Hangar Leases/Bowers Works Part 1 (Box-folder 2-9)
- Hangar Leases/Bowers Works Part 2 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Service Letter/Hydro Swing Mag., 2006-2006 (Box-folder 2-11)
- Bowers Field Airport Master Plan Update, 2001-2001 (Box-folder 2-12)
- - (Box-folder -)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 1, 1993-1993 (Box-folder 3-1)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 2, 1981-1981 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 3, 1977-1977 (Box-folder 3-3)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 4, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 3-4)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 5, 1991-1991 (Box-folder 3-5)
- Kittitas County Airport Land Use Planning Guide Part 6 (Box-folder 3-6)
- Airport Advisory Board Minutes, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3-7)
- Noise/Burbank Part 161 Study, 2002-2002 (Box-folder 3-8)
- Airport Open House (Box-folder 3-9)
- AC 150/5020-1 Noise Control FAA Advisory Circulars, 1983-1999 (Box-folder 3-10)
- Presentation: Bowers Field, 2002-2002 (Box-folder 3-11)
- Residential Development-Bowers Field/Runway, 2001-2006 (Box-folder 3-12)
- Save Airport/Cal. Pilots Assoc. Manual (Box-folder 3-13)
- Security, 2002-2002 (Box-folder 3-14)
- Aviation Taxes/Towers, 2000-2000 (Box-folder 3-15)
- Utah Back Country Pilots Inc., 2003-2003 (Box-folder 3-16)
- Washington Aviation System Plan, 2001-2001 (Box-folder 3-17)
- Kittitas County Planning Commission/Airport Zone Revise/Airport Overlay, 2000-2000 (Box-folder 3-18)
- AOPA-Land Use and Airport Noise/Noise Complaints and Comments, 2000-2000 (Box-folder 3-19)
- NATA/Planning Commission, 2000-2000 (Box-folder 3-20)
- Oregon Airport Land Use, 1994-1994 (Box-folder 3-21)
- - (Box-folder -)
- Bowers Field Zoning Presentation/Noise, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4-1)
- Comprehensive Plan/Airport Industuial Zone, 1997- (Box-folder 4-2)
- Airport Encroach Correspondence, 1997- (Box-folder 4-3)
- Noise/Airport Land Use Planning, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 4-4)
- Aviation Division, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 4-5)
- Airport Zone Proposal, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4-6)
- Airports and Compatible Land Use Planning, 1998- (Box-folder 4-7)
- Museum of Flight, 2002- (Box-folder 4-8)
- CAC Recommended for Airport, 1997- (Box-folder 4-9)
- UGA-Ellensburg CAC Findings and Recommendations, 1997- (Box-folder 4-10)
- Radio Control Bowers/Airport Zone-Spokane, 1996-2007 (Box-folder 4-11)
- Permanent Administrative Rules/Over Zone/ Airport Regulations, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 4-12)
- Zoning-Types Defined, 1977-1993 (Box-folder 4-13)
- Zoning-GPS Prevision Approach, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 4-14)
- Zoning-AOPA/Zoning-Response to Planning Commission, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4-15)
- AC 150/5190-4A Model Height Zoning FAA, 1987- (Box-folder 4-16)
- Noise-Legislative Bills, 2000- (Box-folder 4-17)
- Zone History/Airport Advisory Committee Minutes, 1997- (Box-folder 4-18)
- Bowers Field Master Plan, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4-19)
- Consultant Agreement, 1984-1999 (Box-folder 4-20)
- Kittitas County Airport Master Plan Scope of Services, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 4-21)
- Kittitas County Airport Bowers Field-Presentations, 1999- (Box-folder 4-22)
- City of Forks-Master Plan, 1999- (Box-folder 4-23)
- Brochures Development, no date- (Box-folder 4-24)
- Airport AOPA Compliance Guide, no date- (Box-folder 4-25)
- Airport Photographs and Negatives, 1999- (Box-folder 4-26)
- Zoning Draft-Old Part 1, 1999- (Box-folder 4-27)
- - (Box-folder -)
- Zoning Draft-Old Part 2, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5-1)
- Zoning Draft-Old Part 3, 1997- (Box-folder 5-2)
- Zoning Draft-Old Part 4, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 5-3)
- Goals for Advisory Committee/Slater Field Development, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5-4)
- Lucas and Dolan Regulatory Takings, 1995- (Box-folder 5-5)
- AOPA Nall Report, 1998- (Box-folder 5-6)
- Airport Board, 1996- (Box-folder 5-7)
- Airport Advisory-Bowers, 1995- (Box-folder 5-8)
- Bowers Field Airport, 1998- (Box-folder 5-9)
- ASN/AOPA-Certificate of Appointment, 1998- (Box-folder 5-10)
- Bowers Field Open House, 1998- (Box-folder 5-11)
- Zoning -Maps, no date- (Box-folder 5-12)
- Zoning-Notes, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5-13)
- Bowers Zoning Ordinance, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5-14)
- Development-Miller, John, 1999- (Box-folder 5-15)
- Wolf Aviation Fund, 2001- (Box-folder 5-16)
- Airports and Wildlife, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 5-17)
- Master Plan ELN, 2000- (Box-folder 5-18)
- Master Plan Scope of Works, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 5-19)
- Zoning-Bowers Draft/Zoning-Yakima Airport, 2001- (Box-folder 5-20)
- Development-Jack, Hale/News, 1999- (Box-folder 5-21)
- Airport Zoning, 1999- (Box-folder 5-22)
- ASN Volunteer/Airport Advisory Committee/"Lifestyles News"/Zoning, 1999- (Box-folder 5-23)
- Meadows Development, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 5-24)
- Airport Land Use/Open House, 2009- (Box-folder 5-25)
- General Aviation/Objectives Report/Quttclaim Deed, 1948-2008 (Box-folder 5-26)
- - (Box-folder -)
- Felts Field Spokane, no date- (Box-folder 6-1)
- FAR Part 77, no date- (Box-folder 6-2)
- Bowers Field Approach Study, no date- (Box-folder 6-3)
- Wind Farms Turbines, no date- (Box-folder 6-4)
- Bowers Field Airport Master Plan Update, 2001- (Box-folder 6-5)
- Bowers Field Airport Master Plan Update, 2001- (Box-folder 6-6)
- Bowers Road Extension, 2000- (Box-folder 6-7)
- Oregon Airport Land Use, no date- (Box-folder 6-8)
- Planning for a Large Airport, no date- (Box-folder 6-9)
- Planning for a Large Airport, no date- (Box-folder 6-10)
- Kittitas County Airport Bowers Field Accident Pattern (Box-folder 6-11)
- Bowers Field Approach Study, 1999- (Box-folder 6-12)
- Zoning Draft-Old Part 3 Appendix B, no date- (Box-folder 6-13)
- Kittitas County Airport Bowers Field, no date- (Box-folder 6-14)
- Zoning Draft-Old Appendix, no date- (Box-folder 6-15)
- Zoning Maps, no date- (Box-folder 6-16)
- Zoning-Bowers Draft/Zoning-Yakima Airport, no date- (Box-folder 6-17)
- - (Box-folder -)
- Aviation Scrapbook, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 7-)